<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tvvo sermons preached before his Maiestie, in his chappell at Whitehall the one, the xi. of Februarie, the other the xxv. of same moneth. By Richard Meredeth, one of his Maiesties chaplaines in ordinarie.</title>
            <author>Meredeth, Richard, 1559-1621.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07446</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17832</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103382</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839137</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839137</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3536</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07446)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3536)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1247:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tvvo sermons preached before his Maiestie, in his chappell at Whitehall the one, the xi. of Februarie, the other the xxv. of same moneth. By Richard Meredeth, one of his Maiesties chaplaines in ordinarie.</title>
                  <author>Meredeth, Richard, 1559-1621.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Eld, for Simon Waterson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3536:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TVVO SERMONS Preached before his Maieſtie, in <hi>his Chappell at Whitehall, the one,</hi> the xi. of Februarie, the other the <hi>xxv. of the ſame moneth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Meredeth,</hi> one of his Maieſties Chaplaines in ordinarie.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by <hi>G. Eld,</hi> for <hi>Simon Waterſon.</hi> 1606.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3536:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3536:2"/>
            <head>Text.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Micheas Chap.</hi> 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3, 4, 5.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>O my people what haue I done vnto thee, or wherein haue I grieued thee? teſtifie againſt me, ſurely I brought thee vp out of the land of</hi> Aegypt, <hi>and deliuered thee from the bondage of ſeruants, and haue ſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee</hi> Moyſes, Aaron, <hi>and</hi> Miriam. <hi>O my people remember what</hi> Balaac <hi>the King of</hi> Moab <hi>hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed, and what</hi> Balaim <hi>the ſonne of</hi> Beor <hi>anſwered him from</hi> Sittem <hi>to</hi> Gilgal, <hi>that thou mayeſt knowe the righteouſneſſe of the Lord.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Gods excéeding goodneſſe towards the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> nation and their extreame vnthankefulnes againe towards him, might the more clearely appeare, beeing compared together, the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, that is as S. <hi>Hierom.</hi> faith <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hierom in Michea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Cap.</hi> 6.</note> the elect Angels of heauen, and the mighty foundations of the earth, that is the great <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs</hi> and <hi>Potentates</hi> of the world, beeing ſommoned to be witneſſes of this controuerſie and quarrell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene God and them, the ſpirit of the Lord God in the mouth of the Prophet <hi>Micheas,</hi> the pen of a ready wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, maketh proteſſation in this place of the one, &amp; prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him by open challeng, to auoid if they can in reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the ſhame of the other, and therewithall licenſeth them to diſpute their owne cauſe for themſelues, &amp; to plead a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, eyther to conuince him of wrong done vnto them and iniury, or elſe to condemne themſelues of too much ingratitude towards him and wicked obſtinacie. <hi>O my people</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>what haue I done vnto thee? &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3536:3"/>
It is not my purpoſe (moſt honourable) to cal to your remembrance the manifold benefittes and bleſſings which God from time to time, vnder good leaders, cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, iudges, and kings, hath beſtowed vpon the <hi>Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi> nation, that might be tedious vnto ſome, ſuperfluous vnto others, and impoſſible to me, at this one time, for ſo I might at this time begin and not be able to make an ende, my purpoſe is to come neerer home vnto our ſelues, and to apply in particular the circumſtances of this Scripture vnto theſe preſent times and preſent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, men conſider with better attention thoſe things which they féele to be done vnto themſelues, then they do thoſe things which they heare done vnto others, we beleeue the report of the one, becauſe we haue heard it, our ſelues can teſtifie the certainty of the other, becauſe wée haue ſéene it, as we haue heard concerning them, ſo alſo haue we ſéene concerning our ſelues in the houſe of God.</p>
            <p>God hath as little grieued vs, as euer he grieued them. 1. God hath as aboundantly bleſſed vs, as euer hée bleſſed them, 2. We for our parts haue dealt as vnkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with him, as euer did they before vs. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And therefore he for his part, may as iuſtly conteſt againſt vs as euer he did againſt them, and ſay vnto vs and againſt vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O my people what haue I done vnto thee. &amp;c. Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carpus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb. eccl. hiſt. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</note> beeing required by an <hi>Infidell</hi> Iudge, to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme Chriſt, made him this witty, and deuout anſwer, 86. peeres haue I liued, neither did he once harme me in any one thing, why then ſhould I blaſpheme my God, which hath neither hindred nor iniured me. We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not charge our God with any wrong, our gratious Lord with any hardnes, iniury, or vnkindnes towards vs, but muſt alwayes &amp; euer with <hi>Polycarpus</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his excéeding bounty and vnſpeakeable goodnes. There be but 3. things in the world which the Lord hath alwayes vſed as 3. notable inſtruments, for the filling vp of his ſury, and for the ſpending of his plagues vppon the nations, to wit, Famine, Peſtilence, and the Sword,
<pb facs="tcp:3536:3"/>
chooſe ſaith the prophet <hi>Gad</hi> vnto <hi>Dauid,</hi> whether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wilt haue 3. daies Peſtilence, or whether thou wilt haue 7. yeares Famine in the Land, or whether thou wilt flie 3. moneths before thine enimies, and with which of theſe 3. hath the Lord grieued, I cannot ſay wronged vs, if ſo be, it be a bleſſing and not a puniſhment, to ſtand ſtill void and exempt of all affliction and trouble.</p>
            <p>Firſt as touching Peſtilence, albeit it bee a ſpeciall puniſhment appointed by God himſelfe vnto all thoſe which ſtubbornely diſobey and tranſgreſſe his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, for ſo ſpeaketh God by his ſeruant <hi>Moyſes: If thou ſhalt not hearken vnto the word which I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand thee this day to doe it, I wil make the Peſtilence to cleaue vnto thee, vntill it haue conſumed thee from the land, and ſmite thee with the botch of Aegypt, &amp;c.</hi> And no one nation vnder the couer of the cope of heauen (that we flatter not our ſelues) more ſinfull people then we haue béene, yet ſo farre forth hath the meaſure of Gods mercie and goodneſſe excéeded the meaſure of our ſinne and wickedneſſe, that the fault remayning too ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiuely amongſt vs, the puniſhment for the moſt part hath béene taken away, yea in the verye time of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance and deſtruction, our God bethought himſelfe of mercy and preſeruation, for in the winter ſeaſon he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the Angell to ſmite, and in the ſummer ſeaſon (a mercy beyond all expectation) he commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the deſtroyer to forbear, in one yeare he conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this mighty <hi>Nin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iuie</hi> the great Citty of <hi>London,</hi> to drinke of the cuppe of the wrath of his vengeance, the next yeare following ſpared them, and enforced all the noble Citties of this mighty Kingdome to ſucke out the dregges which were left in that cuppe. At this time he hath gathered many of the arrowes of this his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure into his Quiuer, but ſuffereth ſome of them to remaine ſcattered, that we may learne to feare him which hath power ouer the plagues, to take vp betimes with God, leſt a worſe thing happen vnto vs &amp; ſo occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be giuen vnto GOD to fill vp the meaſure of that
<pb facs="tcp:3536:4"/>
vengeance which he hath begone, and ſo ſwéepe vs all, top and tayle, root and braunch, great and ſmall, young &amp; old, ſuperior &amp; inferior ſweepe vs I ſay al with that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom which the holy Scripture ſpeaketh of, the Beſom of deſtruction.</p>
            <p>For the other inſtrument of Gods iuſtice, (famine of bread and ſcarcitie of foode) this Land hath not this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares béene grieued and afflicted, the Lord hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened his góod treaſure vnto vs, euen the Heauens to giue raine vnto the earth in due ſeaſon: and the earth to giue her encreaſe, the Trées of the field to ſend forth their fruite, the Lord hath made vs happie in the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> euen in the fattneſſe of the earth and the dewe of Heauen. The Lord hath heard the heauens &amp; the Heauens haue heard the earth, and the earth hath heard the Corne, and the Corne hath heard <hi>Iſrael</hi> his people. Howbeit leaſt our long peace ſhould breede vs too much plentie, and our ouer much plentie ſhould make vs too proud, and our pride ſhould pricke vs to play the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton children againſt our gratious GOD, he hath in his Fatherly prouidence tempered our proſperitie with ſome gentle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of moderate correction: to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſome eight or nine yeares ſince, the ſéede became rotten vnder the cloddes, the meate was cut of before our eyes, our old ſtore was ſpent, our garners were emptie, our flocks of ſhéepe were deſtroyed, our heards of cattell were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oded, the ſtarte of bread <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in euery place, the tongue of the ſuckling Child did euen cleaue as it were to the roofe of his mouth, many aſked bread, very fewe brake and gaue vnto them.</p>
            <p>For the third inſtrument of the ſcourge of Gods iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, (warre and the ſword,) of this theſe many yeares we haue not: and I pray God many moe yeares we do not taſt. Inquire the generations of old which were before time, ſince that God created man firſt vpon the earth, and aſke from one end of the heauen to the other, was there euer any nation vnto whom, &amp; vpon whom God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed greater kindnes &amp; fauor then he hath done vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> us
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3536:4"/>
in this behalfe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord hath done aſmuch for vs in this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Iland, as euer he did for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the land of <hi>Goſhan:</hi> through out the whole la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of <hi>Egipt</hi> there was ſwarmes of Flies, and Liece, and Caterpillers, and Blaſting, and Thunder, and Mildew, but in the Land of <hi>Goſhan</hi> where the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were, there was none of all theſe, inſomuch as the Lord ſaith, he would deale wonderfully euen betwéene the beaſts of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and beaſts of <hi>Aegipt.</hi> Altour néere neighbours and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borders round about vs, haue dronken of the fierce cup of the wrath of Gods indignation, hee hath made his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes ſurfeit with blood, and hath made his ſwoord to eate the fleſh of the one, and of the other, but as for vs his beloued, in this little <hi>Iland,</hi> he hath kept vs in ſafetie in a Land which floweth with milke and wheal, and honie, and hath multiplied vs, and hath bleſſed vs, and hath encreaſed vs, and hath enriched vs, both in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of our kine and flocks of our ſhéepe, and heards of our cattell, and hath commaunded the heauens that they ſhould drop vpon vs the fatnes of their dewe, as ſome times they did vpon the little hill of <hi>Hermon,</hi> hee hath amazed the Duke of <hi>Edom</hi> with our happineſſe, he hath caſt the terror of vs vpon the mightymen of <hi>Moab,</hi> he hath made the inhabitance of <hi>Canaan</hi> to quake, and yet for all this, is not the goodneſſe of our God ceaſed towards vs, but yet there is mercie powred on vs ſtill, it is much that he hath giuen vs the Goſpell, it is more that he hath giuen it without any publicke Croſſe and calamitie.</p>
            <p>Surely he hath brought vs alſo out of the Land of <hi>Aegipt,</hi> and deliuered vs from the bondage of ſeruants: ſpeaking of this point, I may iuſtly ſay where may I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne, or where may I end, the matter I am to ſpeake of is much, the time allotted mee to ſpeake in, is but ſhort, loath I am to offend any chaſt or Godly or religious eares, but ſomething muſt be ſaid of it, that we may ſhew our ſelues thankefull for our deliuerance: of religion we are ſometimes perſwaded that it conſiſted onely in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3536:5"/>
obſeruation of a few outward rites and ceremonies, as touch not, taſte not, handle not, which all periſh with the vſage, and after the doctrines and traditions of men. 2. Of faith, that it was onely a bare ſpeculation, full of feare and terror, without any certaine knowledge of, or ſure confidence in the word of God. 3. Of workes, that a man might worke out his owne ſaluation, or if ſo be he had none of his owne, he might buy the ouerplus of the workes of other men, which they call the worke of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erogation, which they cal alſo the treaſure of the church. 4. Ofdeuotion, that ignorance was the mother of it, and pilgrimage the nurſe. 5. Of prayer, that it may be vſed in an vnknowne tongue, and offered to ſtocks, to ſaints, and to Images. 6. Of the ſacrament of Baptiſme, that it might be applied to bels in a mockery, and encombred beſides with infinite ſuperſtitions. 7. Of the ſacrifice of the Maſſe, that it was a ſacrifice propitiatory for the quick and the dead, as if the ſacrifice of Chriſt once offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp vpon the aultar of his croſſe, had not béene ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient. 8. Of the Church, that it could not poſſibly erre, although it departed from the expreſſe word of God. 9. Of the word, that it was but a dead letter written with Pen and Inke, inſufficient without traditions, ambiguous without the interpretation of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> 10. Of the Pope, that he was Chriſt his generall Vicar vpon earth, aboue Kings, aboue Princes, aboue the word of God, greater &amp; of higher authoritie then the Apoſtles. Of theſe things were ſome of vs &amp; our fathers ſomtimes perſwaded, in the doctrine of theſe things were they trained vp, they worſhipped vanities, &amp; honored lies, or if they refuſed ſo to do, the talkmaiſters were ready to lay more heauy burthens vpon them, then euer were laid vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Iſraelits</hi> in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> their goods were ſpoiled, their houſes ranſacked, their liuings forfeited, their lands ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, their bodies impriſoned, themſelues martyred, their goods, houſes, and children ranſacked, looke what curſing, what banning, what hangman, what gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, what torment, what torture, was able to doe, the Saints of GOD did not onely taſte of it, but in full
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3536:5"/>
meaſure drinke of, faggot &amp; fire was as common in their mouths, as <hi>Ad leonem Chriſtiane</hi> in <hi>Licinius</hi> his dayes, but God which was able to deliuer <hi>Daniel</hi> out of the Lyons denne, and <hi>Ionas</hi> out of the whales belly, &amp; the thrée children in the fiery furnace, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſea, whoſe eyes are euermore ouer the righteous, and which is néere enough to al them that cal vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, working their deliuerance when things were moſt deſperate, ſometimes by meanes, ſometimes without meanes, ſometimes againſt all meanes, euen he in the aboundant riches of his mercies, hath freed vs from this ſlauery and tyranny of our conſciences, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel which was defaced, hee hath reſtored vnto this maruailous light, &amp; hath made the beames thereof ſo to ſhine ouer al parts, &amp; corners and quarters of this excellent kingdom: the rich, the poore, the learned, the vnlearned, the great mighty men &amp; potentates in the world are become defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors and maintayners of the ſame, not onely by their profeſſion and by their word, but by their forces and their ſword, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they haue proteſt with their deareſt blood, &amp; yet for al this, is not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodnes of our God cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed towards vs, but yet there is mercies powred out ſtil.</p>
            <p>He hath ſent before vs alſo <hi>Moyſes, Aaron,</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam,</hi> if the wiſh of our hearts were giuen vnto vs in two things, as it was giuen to King <hi>Salomon</hi> in one thing, we could not deſire two greater bleſſings to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen vnto earth by god vnto ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then <hi>Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron:</hi> a good king to rule vs, and a good prieſt to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct vs, now if God in the multitude of his mercies hath giuen vs the fruition of both theſe, how iuſtly then may he ſay vnto vs as vnto the Iewes. <hi>What can I do more?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. <hi>Paul</hi> is very earneſt with the <hi>Corinthians</hi> that they ſhould learne to know themſelues, which is as ſome thinke the firſt point of wiſdom. <hi>Know your ſelues</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>what do you not know your ſelues?</hi> ſo giue me leaue a little to importune, know your ſelues, what know you not your owne ſtate, after God in the multitude of his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3536:6"/>
bleſſings, had giuen vnto you to be gouerned for the ſpace of 45. years vnder the regiment of a moſt heroical, gratious, vertuous, &amp; religious Quéene hee hath in the aboundance of his mercies, giuen you a King to raigne ouer you, O how honorable is the name of a King, for God &amp; the King enterchange names, for the King is a God vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth, and God himſelfe is a King in heauen.</p>
            <p>I will expreſſe all whatſoeuer I meane to ſay co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this matter in an Embleme or miſtery. <hi>The Lord paſt by, &amp; a mighty wind rent the mountaines and tare the rockes, but the Lord was not in the wind, and after</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. King 19.</note> 
               <hi>the wind came an earthquake, but the Lord was not in the earthquake, &amp; after that came fire, but the lord was not in the fire, and after the fire, came a ſmall ſtil voice, and the Lord was in the voyce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the daies of king <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. of renowned memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, true religion began to appeare &amp; to ſhewe forth her head, but this was brought to paſſe with much tumult &amp; hurliburly. Here the L. paſſed by vs in a mighty ſtrong wind renting the mountaines &amp; tearing the rockes, but yet the Lord was not in the wind, <hi>Deus in turbine.</hi> It pleaſed not God to haue a temple erected vnto him in his dayes, I thinke it was becauſe hee was a man as <hi>Dauid</hi> was, a man of Blood.</p>
            <p>After him ſuccéeded K. <hi>Edward</hi> the 6. &amp; in his daies the very foundations of Popery beganne to be ſhaken, whereupon ſundry violent inſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s were attempted, and moſt dangerous conſpiracies were preuented, here the L. paſſed along by vs in an earthquake, but the L, was not in the earthquake. <hi>Deus non in commotione,</hi> no religion eſtabliſhed in K. <hi>Edward</hi> the 6. dayes.</p>
            <p>After him ſuccéeded in the kingdome, Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> and in her dayes was ſéene in England ſuch a fire, as was neuer ſéene from the beginning, and I hope neuer ſhall be ſéene to the ending. Here the Lord paſſed along by vs in the fire, but the L. was not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fire. <hi>Deus non in igne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After her ſucceeded in the kingdome Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of moſt happy and bleſſed memory, and ſhée albeit ſhée
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3536:6"/>
was the voice, yet ſhe was not the ſmall ſtill voyce, the ouerſwaying faction of Popery at home, &amp; the manifold ſuſpitions of practiſes abroad, inforced her to carry her Enſigne vnder his ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner whoſe name is the L. of hoſts, onely in the old Teſtament, but euer the God of peace in the new Teſtament. As a voice ſhe gaue forth <hi>Tanquam ouis ad mactationem,</hi> as a voyce ſhe gaue forth, <hi>Poſui de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um adiutore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meum,</hi> but the noyſe of the warrior, and the report of the Cannon, and the tumbling of garments in blood, and the rumors of warres, and the iuſt ſuſpitions of <hi>Armadoes</hi> and inuaſions would not permit her to be the ſmall ſtill voice, <hi>Sibilus aure tenuis,</hi> ſhe found the Goſpell profeſſed, by her accompanied by the ſword, as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour foretold, <hi>Tinke ye that I am come to ſend peace</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>vpon the earth, I tel ye no, I am not come to ſend peace but a ſword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we haue liued to behold him, who is both the voice and the ſtill voice, <hi>Et ſibilus, &amp; ſibilus aure te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuis,</hi> as a voice he giues out behold, <hi>The Lambe of God</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>which taketh away the ſins of the world,</hi> as a ſtill voice he writeth for his word, <hi>Beati pacifici.</hi> 2. as a voice hee proteſteth, <hi>This is the way walke in it, turne neither to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, nor to the left,</hi> as a ſtil voice he hath made peace with them that are a far off, &amp; with them that are neare, <hi>Pacem his qui longe, Pacem his qui prope,</hi> as a voice reſolueth come of it what may, <hi>I &amp; my people wil ſerue</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.</note> 
               <hi>the liuing L.</hi> as a ſtil voice he engraueth, <hi>Faciem eo in ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem vnam.</hi> 4. as a voice he publiſheth, <hi>Exurgat Deus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipentur inimici,</hi> as a ſtil voice he hath done more then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his noble progenitors, for although <hi>Henricus roſas, yet Regna Iacobus,</hi> as a voice he ſtudieth, he diſputeth, he <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.</note> conferreth to make vs al to be of one religion, on god, on faith, on baptiſme, as a ſtill voice hee laboureth to make vs al to become one nation, <hi>Vt fiat vnus paſtor et vnum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 9. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. <hi>Caſſiodor.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>vnus Rex, vna lex, vnus dux, vna lux, vna ciuitas vna communi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as, omnia ſunt vnum inquit Miliſſus.</hi> We haue liued therefore to inioy him which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> voice to enioy him which is the ſtil voice, <hi>et ſibilus, et ſibilus aure tenuis,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:3536:7"/>
the Lord no doubt of it is in the voyce, the Lord is in the ſtill voyce, and I giue a reaſon, for warres, and tumult, and ſedition, and faction, and ſciſmaticall contention, is like vnto a Cannon ſtone, which makes two walles of one, but peace, and concord, and amitie, and charitie, and vnitie, and vnion, is like vnto Chriſt the corner ſtone, which maketh one wall of two, peace and truth in the dayes of <hi>Ezechia,</hi> we read it, we beléene it, the Goſpell and all quietneſſe in the daies of King <hi>Iames,</hi> we haue it, we enioy it, we haue found him therefore of whom the ſcripture ſaieth, <hi>Rex Pacificus magnificatus eſt ſuper</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Peg. 9.</note> 
               <hi>omnes reges vniuerſae terra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I dauve not vp with vntempered morter, neither doe I powre out the precious oyle of flatterie, to breake that head which vnder Chriſt in his Church is the head of vs all, but I ſpeake the words of truth &amp; ſoverneſſe, of truth in reſpect of the matter, of ſoberneſſe in reſpect of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, and in very reaſon, flattery vſeth not to commend that which is, but that which is not, but rather to this end and purpoſe haue I ſpoken, that which I haue ſaid, that we may be thankfull for the benefit, and with the propheticall King <hi>Dauid,</hi> breake out into praiſes of our peaceable King, ſaying, <hi>Praiſe thy God O Ieruſalem, praiſe thy God O England, for hee hath made faſt the batres of the gates, and hath bleſſed thy children with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thee, he ſetteth peace in thy borders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as God hath giuen vs a good <hi>Moſes,</hi> a méeke King to raigne ouer vs, ſo if he haue giuen vs good Prieſts withall, we muſt néedes confeſſe that he hath loaden vs withall his benefits, aſwell ſpirituall as corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, &amp; temporall, commonly they goe not farre a ſunder, the one is ſubordinate vnto the other, a good King will take order that there be good prieſts So <hi>Salomon</hi> a good king, drpaſed <hi>Abiathar</hi> the high prieſt, &amp; ſet vp <hi>Saadoc:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb. eccl. hiſt. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> ſo <hi>luſtinian</hi> a godly Emperour, depoſed two Biſhops of <hi>Rome, Siluerius</hi> and <hi>Vigilius,</hi> and anthoriſed others, the ſame <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> was wont to ſay, that he had no leſſe care of the church of Chriſt, then of his owne ſoule: ſo <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:3536:7"/>
               <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> and <hi>Valentinianus,</hi> were wont to call themſelues <hi>Vaſſallos Chriſti,</hi> the vaſſals and ſeruants of Chriſt, and how can Kings ſerue Chriſt the King of Kings better, then to prouide for his church a faithfull Miniſtrie, in that ſtate that the flock is that hath no ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard to lead it, or a ſhip toſt in the floods and tempeſts, in the ſea, and hath no Pilot to guide it, or the ſucking child that hath no nurſe to ſéed it: in ſuch ſtate are mens ſoules vnleſſe they haue the Miniſtery of Gods word abiding amongſt them, you are as children, the Preacher is your nurſe, you are as a ſhip toſt with the manifold ſurges and tempeſts of this trouble ſome world, the preacher is your Pilot, ſafely to conduct you to the barbour of reſt, you are as a flock of ſhéepe, your preacher is your ſhepheard to lead you from dangerous bogges, to the moſt wholeſome paſtures of Gods ſacred word.</p>
            <p>It is therefore a moſt incomparable benefit, euen as much as the ſaluation of mens ſoules, to haue a learned <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5.</note> cleargie, and a vertuous Miniſtery, learned, or elſe how ſhould he be able to diſcharge his dutie, to teach, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, to correct, to reprooue, to rebuke, to confute, that the man of God may be made perfect being moſt abſolute to euery good worke, and therefore it is recuited, that he be ſuch a one which hath béene bred vp at <hi>Oxford,</hi> where the Vniuerſitie is, and not at <hi>Stanford</hi> where the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie neuer was, that is of no Vniuerſitie, vertuous, otherwiſe hée will pull downe more by his euill life, then euer he will be able to build by ſound doctrine: the ſaying of <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great is moſt true, we finde it by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to be ſo, <hi>culpa Sacerdotis ruina populi,</hi> in ſignification <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralium.</hi>
               </note> of both theſe, the Prieſt had alwayes a Tablet before his breaſt in the old lawe, in which was written in great let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of gold, <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummin,</hi> in token that he ſhould be a man, both perfect in life, and full and about dant in the word of God.</p>
            <p>Concerning our ſelues, modeſtie forbids me to ſay much, yet neceſſitie inforceth me to ſay ſomething, it is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3536:8"/>
true indéed, neither I, nor any man elſe, with any face, can iuſtifie all thoſe that are amongſt vs, as amongſt the beſt orders that euer were, ſo alſo are there ſome at this day amongſt vs, falſe prophets, deuouring Wolues, wily fores, inſatiable dogs, deceitfull workemen, ſowers of ſedition, vnſauery Salt, idoll paſtors, which haue months and ſpeake not, and if they had monthes could not eat as they deuoure, all were very Idols as they are no paſtors, <hi>Magus</hi> buieth, <hi>Iudas</hi> ſelleth, and ſome <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits</hi> inueſteth, this is the great cancker and calamitie of our time, and no maruaile though it be ſo amongſt vs, for even amongſt the beſt alwayes that euer were, are ſome faulty. <hi>Ruben</hi> amongſt the Patriarchs, <hi>Saul</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Prophets, <hi>Nicholas</hi> amongſt the Diacons, <hi>Iudas</hi> amongſt the Apoſtles, the diuell amongſt the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, théeues and murtherers in the Temple of God, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination of deſolation in the holy place.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding, howſoeuer our miniſtrie be deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or diſgraced by ſome, for theſe and ſuch like other en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ormities, yet for all that, this is true, and the iudgement of thoſe which are very wiſe, learned, and of great expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and much reuerence, confirme the ſame, there neuer was a more ſufficient and a more learned Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, then at this day. Albeit in contention of learning I may bée worſt heard for to ſpeake, being the moſt unlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of all my brethren, yet for all that, we are not ſo farre to ſéeke as our aduerſaries would make the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue, as if we were ſuch men which followed onely the tide and ſtreame of the time and Parliament, religion as they call it, and had neuer ſéene, nor read, nor ſaluted a farre of, the Fathers, the Counſels, the Schoolemen, or Eccleſiaſticall hiſtories.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in a like matter of comparatiue conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwéene him and the falſe Apoſtles, was enforced <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.</note> to iuſtifie his miniſtery after this ſort, they are <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> ſo am I: they are <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> ſo am I: they are the ſéede of <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſo am I: they are the Miniſters
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3536:8"/>
of Chriſt, ſo am I: ſo may I ſay, and moſt iuſtly ſay, betwéene them and vs, they haue ſkill in the tongues, <hi>Hebrew, Greeke,</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> they haue read the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, the Fathers, the Schoolemen, the Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories; ſo haue we: they haue ſtudied the Artes and Sciences, ſo haue wee: now if they can be learned doing theſe things, I what infortunate and vnhappy men are we, which are ſo vnlearned, and yet doe the ſame commonly this luck followeth all them which are profeſſors of the truth.</p>
            <p>Now as theſe men miſlike, as if we lacked learning, ſo are there others which miſlike as much, as though we had more then ſufficient to liue vpon, our ſhip is toſſed betwéene two dangerous gulphes, <hi>Scylla</hi> and <hi>Charibdis. Aram</hi> before, the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> behind, the Papiſts ſéeke our liues, the Atheiſts ſéeke our liuings, our Preachers now adayes, ſay they are no better then <hi>Paul,</hi> then <hi>Peter,</hi> then <hi>Iames,</hi> which were poore men, pouertie with them is a commendable eſtate, with like deuotion as <hi>Iudas</hi> did, what néedeth this waſte ſaith he, this might haue béene ſould for much, and giuen to the poore, not becauſe be had any care of the poore, but becauſe he was a théfe, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 92.</note> and carried the bagge, and héere for <hi>Sions</hi> ſake I will not hold my peace, and for <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> ſake, I will not kéepe ſilence.</p>
            <p>The world hath béene diſpoſed to make themſelues ſport with men of the Church, as <hi>Dionyſius</hi> did by <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tull. de na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu. deor.</note> Idoll, who comming into the Temple of <hi>Apollo,</hi> and finding <hi>Iupiter</hi> cloathed with a very ſtately riche pale of golde, takes it away cleane off from his ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and giues him a coate of Linſie-woolſie: O Sir ſaith he, this is a great deale better for you, it will kéepe you warmer in the Winter, and colder in the Summer.</p>
            <p>Afterwards, finding <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> his ſonne, ſet out for the ornament of his perſon, with a very faire goodly long heard of gould, playes the Barber with him, ſhaues him roundly, O ſir ſaith he, you are but a yong man, there is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3536:9"/>
no reaſon that you ſhould haue a beard, your father hath none. The reſt of the <hi>Images</hi> in the temple holding forth as it were in their hands certaine coſtly rich platters, &amp; veſſels of gould and of ſiluer, vpon which this was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and engrauen, <hi>Bona Deorum.</hi> I mary ſaith hee theſe are the goods of the Gods, and you doe well to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them vs, great reaſon we vſe the goodnes of the gods and ſo leauing a ſcoffe tooke the gold away cleane.</p>
            <p>As he did then ſo haue ſome others done heretofore, I cannot ſay iuſtly ſpeaking the truth that it is done now: the land and yeerely reuenues which our aunceſtors of renowned memory haue beſtowed vpon churches frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the maintainance of good learning and lawes, is now altogether taken away from vs, the good vſe of them, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euil abuſe ſake, this pale of gold was too hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy for our ſhoulders, a garment rather of Linſiwolſye muſt become vs better, I would God they had giuen vs for it either linnen or wollen, for then we ſhould haue ſeene by the way of exchange to haue had ſomething, they haue taken away al ſtone, timber, lead, yron, glaſſe, mannors and lands, and haue left vs iuſt nothing by way of recompence.</p>
            <p>Our Biſhops, which heretofore did weare long beards of Gold euen downe to their girdles, haue béene if not altogether ſhauen, yet ſo nearely cropt and ſhorne, and wot you by whom? forſooth by their ſhéepe, there is one abuſe added more to thoſe 12. abuſes, which S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> noted in his time, <hi>Senex ſine moribus &amp;c.</hi> The ſhéepe moſt monſtrouſly and moſt vnnaturally haue flieced and ſhorne their ſhepheards.</p>
            <p>The whole body of the Cleargie of this land whom our anceſtors before vs had endued with very great and ſufficient liuings for the maintenance of themſelues and reliefe of others, whom alſo theſe men might haue ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, if it had beene but for this cauſe onely, becauſe the Lord hath chalenged as his, and called them his owne portion, towards them how haue theſe men behaued themſelues? ſome of them they haue polled, and ſome of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3536:9"/>
them they haue pilled, and ſome of them they haue fleed, and ſome of them they haue fléeced, and ſome they haue impropriated from them and appropriated to them ſelues, what by prodigality on way and <hi>Simony</hi> another way, the 2. horſleaches daughters, which crie out, giue giue, the faces of the poore cleargie of this land haue bene ſo grinded, and grated, that after ſo many years paſt, that we haue had Kings to be our nourſing fathers and Quéenes to be our <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioel.</hi> 1.</note> nourſing mothers, we may begin with <hi>S. Paul</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church to make tents y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſidue of the palmer woorme hath the cankerworme eaten, and the reſidue of the canker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worme hath the graſhopper eaten, and the reſidue of the Graſhopper hath the Caterpiller eaten, all men ſées this to be moſt true, which now I make bold to deliuer to this mightie preſence, many find it, ſome féele it, few will ſpeake it, no man goeth about to redreſſe it.</p>
            <p>Only that moſt deuout, and religious act againſt the deminution of the poſſeſſions of <hi>Archbiſhopricks,</hi> and <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks</hi> (O King) procéeding on from your moſt royall munificence, and princely pietie and care, hath made a ſtop and a ſtay againſt all future ſacrileges, alienations, depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, honors, hereditaments &amp; poſſeſſion of the Church: for this cauſe ſhall the holy <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim of Leui</hi> ſhine refreſhed, out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt gratious hea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es of the light of your charitie, his deuotion ſhall aſcend ſwéeter then any incenſe in the preſence of God, continually to entreat for you, <hi>Habes enim multos interceſſores,</hi> his prayers ſhall be as ſo many <hi>Legions</hi> of angells euerlaſtingly to gard you, againſt all plots and practizes, againſt all treaſons and treacheries, the naked loynes of the poore ſhall bleſſe him, I meane <hi>Leui</hi> being couered with his fléece, the emptie bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies ſhall bleſſe him, I meane <hi>Leui,</hi> being filled with his morſells, and wée all ſhall bleſſe the memory of you moſt dread Soueraigne, which hath enabled <hi>Leui</hi> to giue, and ſo by giuing to receiue a bleſſing.</p>
            <p>He raigneth vnprofitablie, which is horne and deſerueth not to raigne, ſaith the golden-mouthed <hi>Chriſoſtome,</hi> but he that commeth vnto vs in a double right of nature and ſo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3536:10"/>
much grace; all the bleſſings of both the teſtaments reſt on him, reſt on his, euen ſo, <hi>Amen.</hi> And yet I giue my note in concluſion to this point: <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> are ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in my text, and in a 100. places beſides of holy Scripture, they ſhould neuer be made baſe, by any vile contempt, or abiect beggery, which follow kings ſo néere in the word of God.</p>
            <p>It followes in the Text, <hi>Remember what Balaac the King of Moab hath deuiſed.</hi> As touching the deuiſe of <hi>Balaac,</hi> it was on this wiſe: After that he ſaw that he could not induce <hi>Balaim</hi> to curſe Gods people, he deuiſed a new ſtratageme by the daughters of <hi>Moab,</hi> ſuborned ſome of them thorow their wanton allurements, to entice the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit firſt fornication with them, &amp; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Idolatrie, that in ſo dooing, they might be brought to ſtincke in the noſtrils of God, and being caſt out of his fauour and protection, be made a preſent prey to their eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies the nations. This was the deuiſe of <hi>Balaac</hi> the King of <hi>Moab,</hi> the end of it was to make hauocke of the people of God, the meane to effect it, was firſt forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and afterwards idolatry, the inſtrument, a ſtrange woman.</p>
            <p>The deuiſe of <hi>Balaac</hi> the King of <hi>Moab,</hi> was a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe comming from fleſh and bloud, and a deuiſe to bée wrought by a ſpeciall inſtrument of fleſh and bloud, <hi>viz.</hi> a woman. The deuiſe of this laſt trayterous, Heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, vncircumcized <hi>Moabites,</hi> was a deuiſe not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from fleſh and bloud, or any humane nature, but from the deuill and his Angels, for ſéeing their doctrine is a doctrine of deuils, it followes accordingly, that their deuiſes, be the deuiſes of deuils, as the trée ſuch is the fruit, a proper kinde of religion which diſpenceth with Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and maintaines rebellions. Of hell, the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith, the nouriſhment of it is woode, and much fire, and the breath of the Lord like a ſtreame of Brimſtone <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 10.</note> doth, ſet it on fire, of this we may ſay the nouriſhment of it ſhould haue bin gunpouder, &amp; much fier, &amp; the breath of the deuill, like a ſtreame of brimſtone ſhould haue ſet it on fire.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:3536:10"/>
The Diuell when he threw downe the houſe vpon the children of <hi>Iob,</hi> threw it downe when they were doyng il, to wit, eating, drinking ſporting, &amp; paſtiming, theſe men, worſe then their father the deuill, would haue blowne vp the Parliament houſe men being aſſembled together to do good, the King, the ſtate, the Cleargie, the nobility the gentry, the commonalty, all beeing aſſembled together in one to ſet downe wholeſome lawes, for the good of Gods glory, quietnes of the church, and peace of the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, what a ſtrange monſter is treaſon, which diueth downe to hell, and beneath hel, the very bottomeleſſe pitte of hell, for to hatch deuiſes: for this is the reſolution of treaſon:</p>
            <q>Flectere ſi nequen ſuperos, Acharonta mouebo.</q>
            <p>The Poets fayne of <hi>Cerberus</hi> the Dogge of hell, that he is a Dogge of many heads and we read of <hi>Hydra</hi> the Serpent that he is a Serpent of many heads, which bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cut off ſpring vp againe as faſt as they bee cutts off. Treaſon the very Dogge of hell, the verye head of <hi>Sata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> the old ſubtill Serpent is like vnto <hi>Hydra</hi> a Serpent of many heads, which béeing cutte off, ſprings vp againe as faſt as they be cut off. It is to be wiſhed, nay it is to bée prayed for, that the ſword of Gods iuſtice may ſo cutte them off, or rather ſeare them vp in theſe laſt Traytors, that they neuer ſpring vp againe, and if they doe, let them know there is a decrée againſt them more firme, then the decrée of the <hi>Meads</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> which neuer changeth, <hi>God ſhall wound the head of his enemies, and the hayric ſcalpe of ſuch a one, which goeth on ſtill in his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Remember what Balaac, the King of Moab hath deuiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which the Lord would haue remembred, may not bée forgotten. Remember what theſe heatheniſh <hi>Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall,</hi> rebellious <hi>Moabites</hi> had deniſed, ſeeking they ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked that deuice fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſmoake &amp; breath, &amp; brimſlone of the <hi>Locuſts</hi> of hell, I meane the Ieſuit the fouls Puritant Papiſt, remeber it therefore to al kind of circumſtances,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3536:11"/>
remember the place, they would haue blowne vp the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament houſe, a place next the Temple conſecrated to holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: remember what time, when all the whole eſtate was included in one: remember the engine, by fire and gunpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the fuell of hell: remember the inſtrument, the one <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> like, which was in <hi>Vtram<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> paratus,</hi> he thought to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe heauen by foule deſtructions and maſſakers: remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to what end, <hi>Caligula-like,</hi> at one blowe to haue taken away both King and ſtate, and roote and branch, &amp; Church and religion, and common-wealth and lawes.</p>
            <p>Can this peſtilent deuiſe of this Heatheniſh <hi>Moabites</hi> be forgotten? no, no, it will be remembred whereſoeuer it goes by the marke of infamie. <hi>Ieroboam</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bah,</hi> that made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſinne, <hi>Ieroboam</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bah</hi> which made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſinne: the <hi>Ieſuit</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> child of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to rebell: the <hi>Ieſuit</hi> the child of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to rebell. Let it be remembred to continue more durable againſt them, &amp; againſt their plots, &amp; againſt their practiſes, &amp; againſt their deuiſes, &amp; againſt their deſignes, then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pillers of <hi>Hercules,</hi> as <hi>Gregorie Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zienzen</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Oratio pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma in Iuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum.</note> of his orations againſt <hi>Iulian</hi> the ranagate, <hi>Hanc a me habes ſempiternae ignominiae columnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Herculeis colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ſublimiorem &amp; inſigniore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ſo let this wickednes of theirs ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d againſt them more durable, then the pillar of <hi>Abſolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> then the tower of <hi>Babel,</hi> then the pillars of <hi>Hercules,</hi> then the black Marble pillar in <hi>Paris,</hi> then all the Pyramides of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> to what end? marry to make them ſtinke in the noſtrils of them that are liuing, like a dead carrion, to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate their exceſſes and their outrages for the preſent, and to terriffe the poſterities and generations to come.</p>
            <p>Let it be remembred, that we being the children of God in imitating God, may learne out of euill for to draw good, for as old <hi>Origen</hi> ſaith, God were not omnipotently good, vnleſſe he were able to draw good out of euill, <hi>Malitiam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Origen. in</hi> 4. <hi>cap. Exod.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>non fecit, ſed factam vtitur ea ad neceſſarias cauſas,</hi> ſo it may ſtand with the good and Chriſtian policie, to vſe theſe wicked actions of diſloyall men, to make more ſure preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatiues, for godly Princes, and faithfull ſubiects: <hi>Serpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:3536:11"/>
               <hi>venena depelli medicamentis confectis exſerpentibus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibent,</hi> which ſpeake not bloudily to incenſe, for what hath the pulpit to do with ſtrangling of bloud? and I know that this preſence before whom I ſtand, reſembleth vpon earth the mercy ſeat of God, and goes vnwillingly conſtrained, and ſorrowing out of the ſame, as God himſelfe did, when he ſaid, <hi>Ah I muſt eaſe me of mine enemies, and auenge me of mine aduerſaries,</hi> and therefore I expreſſe my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and pray, that the deuided heads, and the deuided hearts, and the deuided legges, and the deuided armes, and the deuided quariers of theſe laſt traitors, ſo iuſtly execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for their foule offence, may enſample the whole world, neuer to carry a deuided head, or a deuided heart, nor a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided part, nor a deuided tongue, nor a deuided ſoule, nor a deuided thought againſt our déereſt Soueraigne.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding, ſo many plots defeated, and ſo many deliuerances, deliuerance vpon deliuerance, wrought vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this a moſt memorable day of the wéeke, make the King as confident as a Lion, for he knowes, that it is God which hath ſet a crowne of gold vpon his head. and therefore all traitors may as well flie vpon the wings of the winde, or remooue mountaines out of their places, as to depoſe and tranſplant the royall eſtate of Princes, therefore as King <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid, ſo King <hi>Iames</hi> may ſay, <hi>Thou haſt made my mountaine ſo ſtrong that it cannot bee moued, yea al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Gunpowder lye vnder it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a vaine thing for Mole-hils to riſe againſt moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, as the ſame little creatures which we call Wants or Moales, dig frenches, make breaches, and raiſe hillocks, yet by certaine breaches and vents, and hillockes of their owne making, they are diſcouered, ſo to their very letter, albeit theſe traitors did digge vnder the earth neuer ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, and carried their conſpiracies neuer ſo couertly, yet by certaine vents and breaches of their owne making, they haue béene diſcouered, and as the hand writing appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vnto <hi>Baltaſar,</hi> prognoſticated ruine and deſtruction vnto him, ſo a hand writing comming from their ſelues, hath wrought confuſion vnto their plotte, and I hope ſhall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3536:12"/>
worke confuſion to all plottes and practiſes, iſſuing from all fancies and factions for euermore.</p>
            <p>As touching the anſwer of <hi>Balaim</hi> to <hi>Balaac</hi> it was this, Though <hi>Balaac</hi> would giue me this houſe full of gold &amp; ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, I connot paſſe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of the lord, as the lord ſhal put in my mouth, ſo will I ſpeake, I cannot paſſe the commandement of the L. <hi>Balaim</hi> could not, nor would not paſſe the commandement of the L. Popiſh <hi>Balamites</hi> cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord hath bleſſed &amp; bleſſeth them whom the lord hath curſed, but let vs ſee by the way of compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whether they be in better ſtate whom the Lord hath bleſſed, &amp; the Pope hath curſed, or whether they be in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſtate, whom the Lord hath curſed and the Pope hath bleſſed, &amp; this is euident, god hath made them to yéeld vnto vs, and not vs vnto them, he hath ſet vs aboue and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, he hath made vs the head, and not the tayle he hath ſent a faintnes into the hearts of our enemies &amp; ſorrow vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the inhabitants of <hi>Paleſtina,</hi> the L. hath made vs plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in goods, we haue lent vnto others, and not borrowed our ſelues, in our ſtrength and fortifications, the multitude of the valient men of this kingdome, are as the duſt of the earth, &amp; as the ſand vpon the ſea ſhore innumerable. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fatnes of the earth &amp; the fertility of a plentiful ſoile, we eate our bread in plentiouſnes &amp; are fully ſatiſfied, the lord hath bleſſed vs at home, &amp; abroad in all the workes and labours of our hands, &amp; al the deuiſes &amp; executions of our counſels, &amp; that which is more then all this, he hath choſen vs to be a holy, and peculiar people vnto himſelfe, &amp; hath imparted vnto vs his law &amp; commandement. O how beautifull ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are thy tents, O <hi>Iacob</hi> &amp; thy habitations O Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, as the walles are they ſtretched forth, as the gardens by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> riuer ſide, as the Alloe trees which the lord hath planted, as the Cedar trees by the riuers of water, and therefore we care not although the Pope curſe vs, the more y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope <note place="margin">Numb. 22.</note> doth curſe vs, the more the L. doth bleſſe vs, &amp; therefore no doubt the L. doth bleſſe vs, becauſe the pope doth curſe vs.</p>
            <p>All the woorkes of God are done (how ſoeuer they bée done in mercie or in iuſtice) to the honor of Gods glory. Now the end why he hath done theſe and more then theſe for vs, is that we may know the righteouſnes of the Lord,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3536:12"/>
how good and gracious our God is to vs, that hée hath not immeaſurably grieued vs aboue that we can conueniently beare, that he hath kept vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the noyſomnes of peſtilence, biting téeth of famine, &amp; violence of ſword, that he hath fréed vs from the bondage &amp; ſlauery of our conſciences, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon whereof the making of bricke in <hi>Egipt</hi> had bin very tollerable, that he hath giuen vs a moſt milde, a moſt peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able &amp; a moſt religious <hi>Moyſes</hi> to gouerne vs; a learned &amp; ſufficient Cleargie to inſtruct vs, that he hath defealed and diſappointed cleane both <hi>Balaac</hi> &amp; <hi>Moab,</hi> and all their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh deuiſes; and that he hath turned the curſe of <hi>Balaim</hi> into bleſſngs, and hath done for vs more then for any other nation vnder heauen, all this hee hath done that we may know the righteouſnes of the Lord.</p>
            <p>O that we were wiſe, then would we vnderſtand this, we would conſider our latter ende, why ſhould God thus hem vs in on euery ſide? why ſhould he ſet vs ſtill as a ſignet on his right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d? why ſhould he thus tender vs as the apple of his eye? why ſhould he deale otherwiſe with vs then with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of the nations? our part, our meſſe, hath bin <hi>Beniamins</hi> meſſe, fiue times aſmuch as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of our brethren. In euery one of theſe things, God knocketh ſtill at the doore of euery one of our conſciences, he would come in to vs, &amp; he would ſup with vs, he hath beſought vs for theſe many yeares, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a father his children, &amp; as a mother her daughters, &amp; as a nurſe her babes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we would be his people, as he is our God, &amp; that we would be his children as he is our father, or deſpiſe we the riches of the bountifulnes and patience, and long ſufferance of God, not knowing that the bountifulnes of God leadeth vs to repentance? or if not ſo? I feare me he may ſay of vs as heretofore he did ſay of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he that ſhould haue bin vpright when he waxed fat ſporned with his héele thou art fatte thou art groſſe, thou art loaden with fatnes, therefore they forſooke. God that made them, and regarded not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrong hold of his ſaluation, God hath as aboundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bleſſed vs, as euer he did the Jewiſh nation, with whom he conteſted ſo earneſtly in this place, if wee deale as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfully with him as they did before vs, we which know what hath befallen them, cannot be ignorant what in time may befall vs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:3536:13"/>
God of his infinite mercie, for his deare ſon Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, graunt that our end be not worſe then our begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and continuance hitherto hath bin thou O Lord haſt ſent forth ſtrength for vs, ſtabliſh the thing which thou haſt wrought in vs for thy temple ſake, O Lord God at <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> O giue ſaluation vnto <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Sion,</hi> &amp; perpetuate the ſame, kéepe vs, &amp; preſerue vs vnder the ſhadowe of thy wings from this time forth for euermore. If it be thy will from the noyſomnes of Peſtilence that it neuer infect vs, from the biting teeth of famine, that they neuer deuour vs, from the violence of Sword that it neuer come neere vs, &amp; as by a mighty hand thou heſt deliuered vs from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and ſlauery of our conſciences, ſo keepe vs good lord we pray thee, in this freedome &amp; liberty of the goſpel which we al enioy vnder our milde <hi>Moyſes,</hi> that hee may long raigne ouer vs vnder a faithfull cleargie, that they may carefully inſtruct vs. O let y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> malice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked come once to an end, the peſtilent deuiſes of <hi>Balaac,</hi> and the deuiliſh imprecations of <hi>Balaim,</hi> and bleſſe thou thy people: greater bleſſings O Lord then we haue already receiued wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not aſke or deſire: we pray O Lord for the continuance of theſe things, and graunt our requeſt O Lord, euen for thy deare ſonnes ſake, vnto whom with the holy and bleſſed ſpirit, 3. perſons in Trinity, one God in vnity, be rendred all power, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, glory, maieſtie, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice for euer and euer.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:3536:13"/>
            <head>The ſecond Sermon.</head>
            <head type="sub">Text.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16. <hi>verſe.</hi> 23.</bibl>
               <q>Whatſoeuer you ſhall aske the Father in the Sonnet name, ſhall be giuen vnto you.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Promiſe wée haue in theſe words, more excellent, more certaine, and more vniuerſall, then euer as yet hath come, or euer at any time can come out of the mouth of any prince or Monarch, vniuerſall, for that it promiſed all, and excluded nothing, more certaine, for that he promiſeth which neuer decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, <hi>Dabit vobis,</hi> what ſo frée as gift? moſt high and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, becauſe he promiſed to giue from the higheſt, <hi>a Patre,</hi> from the Father.</p>
               <p>Out of the coafer the treaſure may be taken, the coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer is as it were the Father, the treaſure is all grace, <hi>quicquid:</hi> the Key <hi>in nomine meo,</hi> will open to this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
               <p>From the cipher letter, the ſenſe is to be found, the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is as it were the father, therefore aſke the father, the ſenſe is all grace, <hi>quicquid,</hi> the expoſitor <hi>in nomine meo,</hi> will finde out the ſenſe. Therefore that yée pray, and pray effectually in your prayers. 1. Know whom you are to aſke. 2. What things you are to aſke. 3. And what maner you are to aſke. 1. Whom you muſt aſke, the father, <hi>petite patrem.</hi> 2. What things you muſt aſke, <hi>quid,</hi> or <hi>quicquid,</hi> that which is worthy of the name of a thing. 3. In what maner, <hi>in nomine meo,</hi> in the ſonnes name: of euery one of theſe, and firſt of the perſon whom we muſt aſke, and that is the father, <hi>petite patrem.</hi> The moſt mercifull name of father in holy Scripture, giueth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3536:14"/>
vs many things to vnderſtand in God, to wit, aſſentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, eternitie, antiquitie. 1. Generation, ſpiration, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction. 2. Predeſtination, prouidence, gouernment. 3. Creation, diſpoſition, diſtinction. 4. Adoption, gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernation, education. 5. Inſtruction, redargution, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, many more remaine.</p>
               <p>But principally in aſking graces, the name of father implieth two things, which we ought alwayes to ſet before our eyes in prayer, to wit, the power of God, &amp; the will of God, the might of God, and the mercy of God, his great abilitie, and his great loue; for ſo it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth out amongſt men, in aſking any thing of a man, I conſider whether he can do it of his power, and if he can do it of his power, whether he will do it of his loue, and ſo it is with God.</p>
               <p>Therefore theſe two conceits of power and will, of might &amp; mercie, <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> had when ſhe prayed <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.</note> in the behalfe of her brother <hi>Lazarus.</hi> Lord, he whom thou loueſt is ſick: Lord, is a name of power, therefore thou canſt, he whom thou loueſt, therefore I am to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelfe, that in mercy thou wilt reſtore him.</p>
               <p>Theſe two conceits of power and will, the Leaper had when he prayed, <hi>Lord if thou wilt thou canſt make</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>me cleane, vis,</hi> there is the will: <hi>potes,</hi> there is the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: and our Sauiour anſwered to both, to the will, <hi>volo,</hi> to the power, <hi>mundare,</hi> in the Imperatiue moode.</p>
               <p>Theſe two conceits of power and will, of might and mercie, our Sauiour himſelfe had when he praied; <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, althings are poſſible vnto thee, if thou wilt let this cup paſſe away from me:</hi> All things are poſſible vnto <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 27.</note> thée, there is the power: if thou wilt, there is the loue.</p>
               <p>Here the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> doth will, that men ioyne together in their prayers, theſe two; <hi>Semel loquutus eſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 62.</note> 
                  <hi>Dominus duo haec audiui:</hi> God ſpake once, and heard theſe two things from his mouth; <hi>Power belongeth vnto God, and mercie vnto the Lord,</hi> for that he will render to euery one according to his workes, note it: God ſpeaketh onely one thing, he willeth me in my
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3536:14"/>
prayers to call him father: but by this one word father, he will haue me to vnderſtand two things, his power &amp; his loue, his might, &amp; his mercy. And as touching the power, who is more able then the father. 1. The father can do euery thing in his ſonne. 2. The father of the houſhold in the familie. 3. The father of heauen in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. 4. The father of the world in the world. 5. The father of all can do euery thing in all. And as touching the will, who loueth more then a father, and what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall father ſo much as our ſpirituall and heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>If you being euill</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt) <hi>can giue your children good things, if ſo bee they aske them, how much more ſhall your heauenly father giue you good things, if ſo be you deſire them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore as the wittie Bées, when they go about to make their ſwéete hony-combes, licke firſt vpon the ſwéeteſt flowers of the fields and gardens of the world, and then carry the ſwéete ioyce into their hiues, ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you enter to your prayers, fixe your cogitations vpon theſe two ſwéet flowers of power and loue, which you finde in the name of the father, and then carrie the pure ioyce of them into the inward hiues of your ſoules and conſciences, and ſo ſhall you make a moſt precious hony-combe of all ſpirituall deuotion.</p>
               <p>The conſideration of theſe two things, will bréed in vs two other things, 1. humilitie, out of the conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the power of a father. 2. Confidence out of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the loue of a father.</p>
               <p>A moſt potent father, but to ſo great mightineſſe what profound humilitie will be ſufficient. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid,</hi> to humble himſelfe in his Prayers, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times reckoneth vp his naturall defects, as where he <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 22.</note> ſaith: <hi>I am a worme and no man, a very ſcorne and deriſion amongſt men:</hi> ſometimes his originall ſinne, as where he ſaith; <hi>I was borne in wickedneſſe, and in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 51.</note> 
                  <hi>ſinne hath my mother conceiued me:</hi> Sometimes his actuall ſinnes, as where he ſaith, <hi>We haue ſinned with</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.</note> 
                  <hi>our Fathers, we haue done wickedly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:3536:15"/>
And how many things are there to humble vs before the maieſtie of God? ſpeake we one word, make we one becke thinke we one thought, but in God and from God, in him we liue and moue and haue out being. O poore wretched miſerable beggers that we are, that which a great King ſaid of himſelfe may be ſaid of any, <hi>Ego aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mendicus ſum,</hi> let vs aſke then as beggers, acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 29</note> our déepe ſores &amp; wounds of ſin crauing like beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers knéeling like beggers, following like beggers, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portaning like beggers, let vs aſke the father, <hi>petite pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> let vs aſke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> father w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great renerence euen for this, becauſe hee is a father of great power, <hi>pater potestatis,</hi> aſke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, becauſe he is a father of great power, aſke the father w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence, becauſe he is a father of much merey, <hi>Pater miſericordiarum,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.</note> Confidence and aſſurance in aſking graces, is the only ſtrength &amp; marrow as it were of all our prayers, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the holy Ghoſt ſaith, <hi>Si fiduciam habemus apud De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> if wée haue confidence with God, what ſoeuer wée <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh</hi> 2.</note> aſke we ſhall obtaine, now the name of a father imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all confidence. 1. The father is mercifull, therefore <hi>Saluum me fac propter miſericordiam tuam.</hi> 2. Great are the merits of the ſonne of ſo louing a father, therefore <hi>Reſpice in faciem Chriſtitui.</hi> 3. True are the promiſes of the father, therefore fulfill thy word vnto thy ſeruant, <hi>Vt in ſermonibus tuis iuſtificeris.</hi> 4. Can my faults, can my defects, can my vanities ſet a barre againſt me, and the father? I ſet againſt my faults the mercy of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, againſt my defects the merits of the ſonne, againſt my vanities, the inward comfort and conſolation of the holy Ghoſt, and therefore I implore, I beſéech, I intreat I importune, I am inſtant, in ſeaſon and out of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon onely let not my heart condemne mee of any ſoule or groſſe thing, and then praying to the father in Thriſts name, and for ſuch a thing as I ought to do, I ſhall be ſure to obtaine: ſo the holy Scripture, <hi>Si cor noſtrum nos non reprehendit, tunc fiduciam habemus apud Deum.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:3536:15"/>
Haue you euer marked that when you would looke vpon the ſunne, your eyes béeing not able to behold ſo great a light, yee vſe the defence of your hands, and the ſame ſunne cauſeth the reflection of a ſhadow from both your hands vnto your breaſts, I muſt tell you, God the Father is the true bright cleare ſunne, vnto whom you may not approach with ſo confident an eye to aſke gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, without the interpoſition of theſe two hands of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and leue, which you haue in the name of Father, and the interpoſition of theſe too, will cauſe a ſhadow to reflect vpon your breaſt, that is, will worke in you good deſires, good purpoſes, and vertuous actions whiles out of the conſideration of the power of the father, riſeth humility, and out of the conſideration of the loue of the Father riſeth confidence, theſe are 2. legges, 2. armes, 2. wings which will carry vs into heauen, two things very néedefull and neceſſary in our prayers, and both are produced in conſidering God as a Father.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>Secunda pars.</head>
               <p>But to riſe a point higher, from the perſon whom we muſt aſke, to the thing what wee muſt aſke, what may we aſke, nap what thing may we not be bould to aſke? <hi>Si quid, ſi quid,</hi> without any limitation, <hi>quicquid, quicquid,</hi> without any determination. All fauour, al goodneſſe, all grace, all glory, all this may I aſke as much as you can ſée, as much as you heare, as much you can belecue, as much as you can hope for, all this may you aſke, temporall things for the world, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall things for the ſoule, corporall things for the bodye, eternall things for glory, all this may you aſke.</p>
               <p>What will ye that the heauens be ſhutte vp? <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> aſked it and obtayned, that the heauens bée opened, the ſame deſired it, and had it. That the Sunne ſtand ſtill, <hi>Ioſua</hi> aſked it and obtayned it, that the Sunne goe back ward, <hi>Ezechias</hi> deſired it, and had it. That
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3536:16"/>
fire come downe from heauen, <hi>Elias</hi> aſked and obtained it: that waters ſpring out of the rocks, <hi>Moyſes</hi> aſked it and had it.</p>
               <p>That the floods and waues ſuſtaine yée? <hi>Peter</hi> aſked it and obtained it: that the dead riſe againe, ſundrie haue aſked it, and haue had it.</p>
               <p>What will ye, wiſdome? <hi>Salomon</hi> aſked it and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained it. Grace? <hi>Dauid</hi> aſked it and had it.</p>
               <p>Heauen and Paradice? the Theefe aſked it and obtaned it, <hi>quicquid, quicqud,</hi> without any limitation, <hi>ſi quid, ſi quid,</hi> without anie determination, and to the reaſon, we may aſke all of him, which can giue all, we may aſke all of him which will giue all, <hi>voluntate labiorum non fraudabo te,</hi> ſaith God, I will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraude the deſire of thy lippes, you may aſke all there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, euen as much as your tongue can ſpeake, or heart imagine.</p>
               <p>And for this cauſe we Chriſtians, though we be poore, yet are we the richeſt of all other Creatures, note it, for Cattell and bruite beaſts, nature hath prouided foode and ſuſtenance, and many getteth it only by his work and labour God hath clothed beaſts which ſkinnes, and the trees with barke, man only is borne poore and naked, the beaſts haue for armour to defend them both hornes and hoofes, and téeth and cloues, man onely is borne diſarmed in all, the open ayre hurteth not them, man ſcarce defendeth himſelfe with houſes and buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges, the life of all other things is quiet and ſecure, and this life of ours, wee know not how to tearme it, a life or a death, ſurely, if not a perpetual ſhipwracke, yet a continuall warfarre, neuertheleſſe the beaſts make no requeſt, but man requeſteth, theſe Creatures vſe no praiers, man praieth, now if by this meane of praier, hée may get, all what ſoeuer is behoueable for him, <hi>quicquid petiaritis,</hi> who can be more rich, or who can be more wealthy then a Chriſtian?</p>
               <p>All vniuerſalitye is in this word <hi>quicquid,</hi> or <hi>ſi quid,</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:3536:16"/>
wée may aſke and obtaine it, ſo that it bée <hi>quid,</hi> that is worthye of the name of a thing, now hée that prayeth God will further him in his ſinnes, prayeth not for <hi>quid,</hi> but for <hi>nihil, Sine ipſo factum eſt nihil,</hi> God made not ſinne, ſo doth Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> conſter it, Sinne deſtroyeth in vs the true <hi>quid,</hi> which is good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and maketh a man as nothing, or worſe then nothing, <hi>Quia melius nihil eſſe quam infaeliciter</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.</note> 
                  <hi>eſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore it is ſaid of the child of perdition, that it had béene good for him he had neuer béene borne: that man therefore that prayeth that GOD will helpe him in his ſinnes ſhall not bée heard, becauſe hée aſketh not <hi>quid,</hi> but <hi>nihil,</hi> witneſſe the Prophet <hi>Dauid, Si iniquitates aſperunt in corde meo, dominus non exaudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, If there be any iniquity in my heart, the Lord will</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>not heare me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, note farther, not onely hée that aſketh not <hi>quid,</hi> receiueth not <hi>quid,</hi> but hée that aſketh <hi>nihil,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth <hi>nihil,</hi> hée that aſketh nothing, receiueth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, he that aſketh ſinne, receiueth ſinne, for in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a ſinne, he committeth a new ſinne, and ſo his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry prayers are turned into ſinne, according to that in the Pſalme, <hi>Fiat oratio eius in peccatum, Let his praier</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 102.</note> 
                  <hi>be turned into ſinne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In an other ſenſe doth <hi>Gregory</hi> the great expound this word, this word <hi>quicquid,</hi> as <hi>ſi quid,</hi> that is, that ye aſke <hi>quid,</hi> &amp; not <hi>quale,</hi> that is, that ye aſke ſubſtances &amp; not accidents, that is, that ye aſke ſubſtantiall things, and not vayne things, that is, that yee aſke perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent things, and not tranſitory things, for all theſe corporall and worldly things beeing compared to ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and eternall things, are not <hi>quid,</hi> but <hi>quale,</hi> va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, toyes, leaues, trifles, ſhadows, ſmoke, nay that are nothing, or very neere nothing, they are the <hi>nihil,</hi> or very neere to the <hi>nihil,</hi> I ſay, and will proue it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Either nothing for this cauſe, becauſe manye
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3536:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in ſéeking after them by ſundry feares &amp; cares, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moyles, and tumults, and labours, &amp; vexations, do waſte and conſume their vitall ſpirits, and ſo bring themſelues to nothing, according to that of <hi>S. Auſtine, propter talia ſe homines a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nihilant imitando, inſidiando, machinando, bella<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ad fratres in eremo.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Or nothing for this cauſe, becauſe they auaile and helpe vs nothing in the fearfull triall of examination, and ſeueritie of iudgment, according to the cenſure of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Dormierunt ſomnum ſuum &amp; nihil inuenerunt:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 54.</note> the rich men of this world haue ſlept their ſléepe, &amp; found nothing, for their bodies muſt to the earth, their riches to the world, their ſoules to iudgment, &amp; ſo there is nothing left of all that euer they had to plead for them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Or nothing for this cauſe, becauſe they neuer ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate or content the ſoule, for the ſoule hauing receiued many of them, deſireth ſtill to receiue more of them, as if ſhe had receiued nothing at all, according to that experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> found to be true in his owne heart. <hi>The eye is not ſatiſfied with ſeeing, nor the eare with</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>hearing.</hi> Can honors ſatiate the ſoule, many great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours were vnto <hi>Hamon,</hi> and yet he is diſcontented in reſpect of <hi>Mardochay. All this can nothing auaile me,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>as long as I ſee Mardochaie the Iew ſitting at the Kings gate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Can pleaſures ſatiate the ſoule? <hi>Salomon</hi> had his eyes, his eares, his hands, his heart, full of pleaſure, and yet he cries out: <hi>All things are full of labour, and man cannot expreſſe them, can riches ſatiate the ſoule?</hi> Of &amp; againſt couetous rich men, God ſaith: <hi>Yee eate and are not fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, yee drinke and are not ſatiſfied, yee cloth, yee, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hagge.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>yee are not warmed, he that earneth money, putteth the ſame into a bottomleſſe bagge.</hi> Can humane learning, can learning ſatiate the ſoule? the Philoſophers excelled in this, yet Saint <hi>Paul</hi> obbraideth them, where is the ſcribe, where is the learned, where is the diſputer of this <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</note> world, is not the wiſdome of this world fooliſhneſſe before God can territories, can dominions, can Empires, ſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the ſoule? <hi>Alexander</hi> hearing that there were thrée
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3536:17"/>
worlds wéept bycauſe he had got but one of them of whome this verſe was made.</p>
               <q>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus Pilleo iuueni non ſufficit orbis.</q>
               <p>For <hi>de opibus praua,</hi> of riches comes wicked thinges, <hi>de voluptatibus turpia,</hi> of pleaſures comes filthie things, <hi>de honoribus vana,</hi> of honors comes vaine thinges, all <note place="margin">Innocentius</note> tends to that which the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> an eye wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſaw, <hi>aſpexi terram et ecce erat inanis &amp; nihil,</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beld the whole face of the earth and behold it was emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 4.</note> and nothing, emptie, for that it had no fulneſſe in it to ſatiate the ſoule, and nothing, for that it was ful of ſinne to defile the ſoule. And therefore pray not ſo much for honors, or riches or treaſures, or pleaſures, or health or wealth, or proſperitie, and ſuch like: theſe are not the eſſentiall <hi>quid,</hi> but the accidental <hi>quale,</hi> nay they are nothing in compariſon of the true <hi>quid,</hi> heare the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.</note> cenſure of the wiſeſt King, <hi>diuitias nihil duxi in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione illius,</hi> I eſtéeme riches nothing in compariſon of wiſdome, and if hee eſtéeme riches nothing in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of wiſdome, the whole world eſtéemes al the reſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in Compariſon of riches for.</p>
               <q>Et genus et formam regina pecunia donat.</q>
               <p>And therefore for honors and riches and treaſures and pleaſures, and health, and wealth, and proſperitie, wée pray not abſolutely but conditionally, ſo farre forth as they tend to the true <hi>quid,</hi> that is to the glory of God, &amp; bettering of our ſoules, for that petition for temporall things, <hi>Panem nostrum quotidianum da nobis,</hi> hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes a reference to the other petitions for grace and glory: <hi>idueniat regnum tuum, fiat voluntas tua,</hi> to ſhut vp all in one, if ye aſke that which is euill, you ſinne and aſke nothing, in that ye aſke that which is worſe then nothing, if ye aſke temporary things only, ye erre, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye aſke not the ſubſtantial <hi>quid,</hi> but accidental <hi>quale,</hi> ſhadowes not ſubſtances, if ye aſke them in a diſorderly manner, preferring temporall things before ſpirituall things, you aſke amiſſe, becauſe you would
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3536:18"/>
imploy them vpon your luſts.</p>
               <p>If you aſke them conditionally, ſo farre foorth as they tend to the true <hi>quid,</hi> to the good of the glory of God, and ſaluation of the ſoule: you aſke that which by good vſage may be made <hi>quid,</hi> although in it ſelfe it <note place="margin">Antonius.</note> be not the true <hi>quid,</hi> for as a wittie Schooleman ſaith, Temporall things ſtand as things indifferent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene <hi>quid</hi> and <hi>nihil,</hi> the good vſage of them makes them to be <hi>quid,</hi> the bad vſage of them brings them <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sermone</hi> 3. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> to <hi>nihil,</hi> for as holy <hi>Barnard</hi> ſaieth; <hi>Vſus eorum bonus, abi ſus malus, ſollicitudo peicr, queſtus turpior,</hi> the vſe of them is good, the abuſe of them is naught, ouer much care to get them is worſe, and béeing euilly gotten, and prodigally ſpent, they prooue worſt of all: but the beſt way is alwayes to aſke that which is <hi>quid,</hi> which is worthy of the name of a thing. Foure things may we aſke which are the true <hi>quid:</hi> to wit, Remiſſion of ſinnes, Grace, Perſeuerance, and Glorie: in the <hi>te Deum,</hi> which is ſung in the Morning prayer, you haue all theſe; for remiſſion of ſinnes, <hi>Lord ſaue thy people:</hi> for grace, <hi>And bleſſe thine inheritance:</hi> for perſeuerance, <hi>And gouerne them:</hi> for glorie, <hi>And lift them vp for euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thrée things you may aſke which are the true <hi>quid:</hi> Mercie for that which is paſt, Grace for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and illumination for the future. In the Pſalme which is ſayde in the Euening prayer, yée haue all theſe: for that which is paſt, <hi>God bee mercifull vnto vs:</hi> for that which is preſent, <hi>And bleſſe vs:</hi> for that which is to come, <hi>And ſhew the light of thy counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance vpon vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Two things yée may aſke which are the true <hi>quid,</hi> to eſchew euill, and doe good, <hi>Declinare a malo, facere bonum,</hi> What will yée that the <hi>quid</hi> be one and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular? Heare the Prophet <hi>Dauid, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num petij a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 88.</note> 
                  <hi>One thing haue I deſired of the Lord, and I will not ceaſe to require the ſame, that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord, to behold the beautie of</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:3536:18"/>
                  <hi>his countenance, and to viſit his Temple:</hi> But in this one thing there are all things: And therefore as Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſaieth; <hi>Ama vnum bonum in quo ſunt omnia bona,</hi> Loue one thing, in which are all things: <hi>Pete vnum bonum, in quo ſunt omnia bona,</hi> and yée haue enough.</p>
               <p>For 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if ye be delighted with beautie, here the iuſt ſhall riſe, and ſhall ſhine as the firmament; and they that lead many vnto righteouſneſſe, ſhall ſhine as the ſtarres for euer &amp; euer, 2. if with a long and healthfull life, here ſhall be healthfull eternitie, and euerlaſting ſanitie, for the bodies of the Saints ſhall liue for euer, and their health is from the Lord. 3. If for fulneſſe and ſatietie, here the Saints of God ſhall be made drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <note place="margin">Bonauent. de diala ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutis.</note> with the riuers of Paradice, they ſhall bée filled with the beautie of Gods countenance. 4. if for concord or charitie? here the Saints of God ſhall loue God better then themſelues, and their bretheren as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and God ſhall loue them better then they can loue their owne ſelues, and they ſhall loue God and themſelues, and their brethren, for Gods ſake; and God ſhall loue them all for his owne ſake. 5. If for power &amp; abilitie? here the will of Gods Saints ſhall haue an omnipotent operation, for as God can doe all things whatſoeuer he will by himſelfe, ſo they ſhall doe all whatſoeuer they will thorough God. 6. If with honour and dignitie, here God ſhall make his faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, honours ouer much, euen heyres of immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and heyres of a kingdome, and fellow heyres with Ieſu Chriſt: Therefore aſke this one thing with the Prophet <hi>Dauid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and yée haue aſked the true eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall <hi>quid,</hi> in which are all things, and ſo much of the ſecond.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>Pars tertia.</head>
               <p>In the third place, I obſerued the meane how wée come to obtaine all thoſe things which is néede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and behooueable for vs, and that is by offering vp
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3536:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
our prayers in the ſonnes name. In the ſame little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments which are made with many whéeles, one within the other, and each of them hauing imprinted vpon them ſondry letters, vntill you turne them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and backward, in ſuch ſort, that the ſtraight line do direct to euery letter, it is impoſſible that the order of opening ſhold be diſcloſed or that drawne out which is faſt incloſed. The Father is the fountaine and ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of graces, from the aboundance of whoſe ſtreame, all manner of grace and goodneſſe doth flowe, ſo ſayth Saint <hi>Iames, Euery good and perfect gift com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from aboue, and proceedeth from the Father of lights,</hi> howbeit as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>He dwelleth in the light which no man can attaine vnto to diſcouer him,</hi> therefore vnto vs, and to open all the treaſure incloſed in him, behold the ſtraight line, behold the true letter, <hi>Petite in nomine meo,</hi> aſke in Chriſts name, and you ſhall obtaine.</p>
               <p>But here it may be demaunded what it is to aſke in Chriſts name, <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> ſaith, that then we aſke in the name of Ieſus, which ſignifies ſaluation, when as we aſke nothing elſe, but that which appertaineth to ſaluation, S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſaith, that then we aſke in the name of Chriſt, which ſignifieth annointed when as we are annointed in the faith and vertues of Chriſt: the word <hi>Nomen</hi> according to the Scriptures, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſignifieth authority, as to baptize in the name of Chriſt is to baptize out of the authority of Chriſt: ſometimes to haue ſuch a name, ſignifieth to be ſuch an one as his name ſhalbe called <hi>Emanuel,</hi> that is by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation God with vs, ſomtimes the word name is taken for the vertue of the merit of Chriſt, as where it is ſaid, <hi>At the name of Ieſu Chriſt, euery knee ſhall bowe, the things in heauen, the things in earth, and vnderneath the earth,</hi> That is, giue thankes for the vertue of Chriſts merit, Angels in heauen ſhall bowe their knees, for that <hi>implentur ruinas,</hi> there ſeates are filled vp, and men on earth, for that their ſinnes
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3536:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
are remitted, and the bodies of faithfull perſons vnder the earth, for that they are to be reſtored to the fulneſſe of life, and therefore with <hi>Cirrell</hi> I take the word, <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> in the laſt ſenſe for the vertue &amp; merite of Chriſt, and ſay that <hi>Petere patrem in nomine Chriſti,</hi> Is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him, not to looke vpon any vnworthineſſe in vs, but vppon the worthineſſe of his ſonne, <hi>Reſpice in faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em Chriſti tui.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus you ſée, it is not enough in your prayers to aſke ſuch a one, that is ſuch a perſon, ſuch a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or ſuch a gift, or ſuch a grace, but you muſt haue a ſpeciall care in vertue, of whoſe merit you aſke that gift, not in the vertue of the merit of Patriarke, or Prophet, Angell or Archangell, Saint, or Saints, but in the vertue of the merit, and ſatiſfaction of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus <hi>in nomine meo,</hi> there is the meane.</p>
               <p>The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> vſeth many arguments and reaſons, by the which (as he thinkes) hee might and ſhould preuaile with God in his prayers, of the which ſome are drawne from GOD, ſome from himſelfe, others from externall things. 1. From GOD, heare me O Lord for that thou art mighty, heare mée for thy mercye ſake, heare me for that thou vſeſt to take compaſſion, heare mée that thou mighteſt bée iuſtified in thy ſayings. 2. From himſelfe heare me, for that in compariſon of others, I may ſéeme to bée righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, heare me for that I haue waſhed my handes in innocencie, heare, mée for my ſoule truſteth in thée, heare mée for that I am abandoned of all others. 3. From externall things, heare me for the reproach of the enemy, heare me, why ſhould hee tryumph this day ouer mée, heare me, why ſhould he ſay to my ſoule there, there, ſo would we haue it, heare me, why ſhould the enemy blaſpheme thée thus dayly? thus the deuout king <hi>Dauid</hi> laboured by all poſſible meanes, to preuaile with God in his prayers.</p>
               <p>But to ſay truely, we haue a more pregnant and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3536:20"/>
vrgent motiue to obtaine at Gods handes, and that is <hi>Petere patrem in nomine Chriſti,</hi> a name which the Sinagogue neuer vſed for ordinary, for they neuer went higher then to pray, <hi>propter Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Iſaac, et Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ierem.</hi> 12.</note> calling on the father Enigmatically in the vertue of the promiſed ſéede, which was to iſſue out of theſe Patriarches loynes: and the moſt illuminate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, neuer vſed this name but figuratiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when they prayed, <hi>Reſpice in faciem Chriſti tui,</hi> nay the Apoſtles themſelues were not come to this high manner of praying as to aſke in Chriſts name: And therefore our Sauiour tells them in this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: <hi>Vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> modo nihil petieritis,</hi> hitherto ye haue aſked no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in my name, and exhorteth them, aſke and ye ſhal obtaine.</p>
               <p>And as the Apoſtles of Chriſt, ſo the Church of the Apoſtles, learned to offer vp theyr prayers in the name of Chriſt: concluding euery prayer and Collect as you may ſée in the communion booke with this clauſe, <hi>Per Ieſum Chriſtum Dominum noſtrum,</hi> Through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, O moſt bountifull Lord of whom we may ſay. <hi>Petimus te, per te, et propter te.</hi> Wee aſke <note place="margin">Gloſſ. ord. in loco.</note> thee, we aſke by thée, and wée aſke for thee, wee aſke thee in that thou art God, we aſke by thee, in that thou art our mediatour, we aſke for thee, in that by the vertue of thy merit, all our prayers are founded and grounded.</p>
               <p>To make your prayers to bee effectuall, many conditions are to bée required. 1. Let your prayers bée fitly and aptly prepared, for a medicine which is prepared, helpeth, and not prepared, hurteth. 2. Let it bée innocent and pure for the ſpouſe then pleaſeth the Bridgrome beſt, when ſhee is a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, and beautifull<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3. Let it be mentall and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, as occaſion is offered, for deuotion like the fire of Willowe, vnleſſe it be blowne, it will goe out and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3536:20"/>
die. 4. Let it bee well deſpoſed and quiet, for the harmonie delighteth not where there is a noyſe. 5. Let it be diſcreete and wary, for ſalte is alway conuenient to a ſacrifice. 6. Let it be faithfull and humble, for humilitie aduanceth vs, and faith ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth God to ſtoupe. 7. Let it be lifted vp on high, for a pigme muſt be lifted vp aboue his owne meaſure, to talke with a giant. 8. Let it be deuout and ſincere, for the incenſe vnleſſe it bée put on fire ſinelleth not. 9. Let it be forcible and ſtrong, for the darte with the more force it is caſt, the farther it flieth, and déeper it pierſeth. 10. Let it be full of loue and ardent, for the Iron burning, pierſeth more then when it is colde. 11. Let it be moiſt and wéeping, for with that tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature the hardeſt ſtone is diſſolued. 12. Let it bée bold and importune, for the ſilly whelpe after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſes, obtaineth the morſels at his maſters table. 13. In a word to ſay all, let it be in Chriſtes name, for an oyntment powred forth, made the whole houſe to ſmell, and Chriſts name is an oyntment powred forth, <hi>oloum effuſum nomen tuum,</hi> not only an oyntment, as holy <hi>Barnard</hi> well noteth, <hi>quia lucet praedicatum,</hi> for it ſhineth while it is preached, <hi>paſcit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ecogitatum,</hi> for that it féedeth, whileſt it is thought vpon, <hi>lenet inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> for that it quieteth the conſcience whiles it is called vpon, but <hi>oloum effuſum,</hi> an oyntment powrod forth powred forth, for that maieſtie tooke vpon it, humility, power tooke vpon it infernitie.</p>
               <p>The mightie GOD became the prince of peace, the wounderfull became the councellor, <hi>Ego dominus, et ego dominus,</hi> became <hi>miſericors, et miſerator Dominus,</hi> powred forth vpon men, vpon Angles, vpon Saints, vpon ſinners, vpon bonde, vpon frée, vpon male and female; powred forth from heauen vnto earth, from the eaſt to the weſt, from the Iewes to the gentles, from the Grecians to the <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> from the knowen word, to the vnkowen world,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3536:21"/>
from Ieruſalem, to <hi>Tubal,</hi> and <hi>Iapan,</hi> the Iſles a farre off, powred forth like the oyle of the widowes cruſe of <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>repta,</hi> tooke greater aduantage, for of one Chriſt, is riſen a whole world of Chriſtians, powres forth like the pretious oyntment which ranne downe <hi>Arons</hi> beard, vnto the ſkirts of his garment, for we haue all receiued of his fulneſſe, grace for grace: powred forth, for the holy oyntment of the Arke of Gods Teſtament, the ſauor and ſwéetneſſe of that oyntment, drew on all the Iewes to follow the Arke, and the ſwéete ſauor of Chriſts vertues, had drawne on all the world in the name of the ſonne to worſhip the father. <hi>Petite in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine meo,</hi> Aſke in my name, a name of greatneſſe, a name of maieſtie, a name of ſaluation, a name of glory, a name of greatneſſe, his name ſhall be called wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, counſellor, the mightie God, the euerlaſting father, the prince of peace, a name of Maieſtie at the name of Ieſus Chriſt, euery knée ſhall bowe, the things in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, the things in earth, and things vnderneath the earth, a name of ſaluation, there is no name giuen vs vnder heauen, by the which we may be ſaued, but only in the name of the Lord Ieſu Chriſt, a name of glory, in him are hid all the treaſures of wiſdome, knowledge and vnderſtanding, becauſe it pleaſeth the father that in him all fulneſſe ſhould dwell. <hi>Petite in nomine meo,</hi> aſke in my name, which hath bin derided by the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, ſcorned of the Iewes, abuſed of the Heretickes, perſecuted by tyrants, and trembled at by the diuels, but within ſhort time ſhall eate idolatry from the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, ſuperſtition from the Iewes, the Church vſurped from the heretickes, the fierceneſſe to ſhed blood from tyrants, and the very ſeates of heauen from the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate flocks of diuels, <hi>Aske in my name, and yee ſhall receiue,</hi> and my heauenly father <hi>Dabit vobis,</hi> ſhall giue vnto you.</p>
               <p>You will ſay perchance, yée haue aſked many times in this name, yet haue not béene heard: but I ſay vnto you, that yée were more then heard, when as it ſéemed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3536:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
vnto you yée were not heard. Foure wayes there bée by the which God imparteth his fauour and goodneſſe, and graces vnto vs. 1. By deferring grace. 2. By changing grace. 3. By denying grace. And 4. by kindling our zeale to aſke grace. What ſaith the zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous man and woman? that they haue praied for feruor of ſpirit, and could not be heard, yée but if God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto them to be ſorrowfull, with a godly ſorrow, for the wante of this feruour, behold grace granted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, by deferring of grace. 2. What ſay the ſonnes of <hi>Zebedie?</hi> that they haue aſked <hi>dextram &amp; ſiniſtram,</hi> and could not be heard yée but if God hath giuen vnto them, to drinke of the bitter cup of his paſſion, that for this they might receiue a greater crowne of glory, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold grace giuen by changing of grace. 3. What ſales the luxurious? what ſay the wantons? what ſay the ambitious? what ſay the couetous? that they haue aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked pleaſures, and honours, and riches, and could not be heard: I but if God had giuen them, they would haue miſpent them vpon the lewd ſhamefull luſts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold grace here giuen by denying of grace. 4. What ſay the hipocrits, the worldlings, the Athieſts? that they haue prayed in his name, and could not be heard: I but they prayed faithleſſely, I but they praied coldly, I but they prayed Kemiſſely: when they ſhall pray faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and feruently, and deuoutly, they ſhall be heard, behold grace here granted, in quickning our zeale to aſke grace. And ſurely that oftentimes yée aſke and do not receiue, yée ſéeke and doe not finde, yée knocke and it is not opened vnto you, either it is becauſe when yée pray, yée curſe, and that is, to ſay the Popes and deuils <hi>Pater noſter:</hi> or elſe it is, becauſe yée aſke amiſſe, as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith: or elſe it is becauſe although yée aſke honeſt things enough, yet not according to Gods will, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did: or elſe it is becauſe yée pray vainly, as <hi>Zebedeus</hi> the wiſe did, or elſe it is becauſe yée pray proudly, as the Pharaſies did: or elſe it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe yée pray with your hands full of bloud, as the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3536:22"/>
Iewes did: or elſe it is becauſe yée pray ignorantly as the Papiſts did, or elſe it is becauſe yée pray faithleſſely and coldly, as the Athieſts doe. If any fault be, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect is on our ſide, on Gods part, this promiſe remaineth firme, <hi>quicquid petieritis,</hi> whatſoeuer yée ſhall aſke the father in the ſonnes name, ſhall be giuen vnto you.</p>
               <p>O moſt powerfull, and profitable, and holy prayer, the comfort of the ſoule, the key to grace, the Ladder to heauen, the entrie to ſaluation, a moſt rich field of <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> a moſt endleſſe fountaine of Paradice, the heart of the ſpirit, the ſpirit of the life, the life of him that liueth well. Now the reaſon why I haue thus magnified and extolled this holy exerciſe of prayer, is to diminiſh and abate the credit, of a certaine new-fangled, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licentious opinion which is of late conceiued amongſt men, to wit, that all the chiefe parts, and points of the chriſtian religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſiſteth in the reading of ſcriptures, frequenting of Lectures, and hearing of Sermons, and here it is neceſſarie that I preface, leaſt I be miſtaken. Therfore as <hi>S. Iames</hi> is not to be vnderſtood to diſpraiſe faith, when as he preferred charitie before it, in reſpect of continuance, nor almes déeds, nor martyrdom, when as he preferred charitie before them both, in reſpect of the dayly vſe, nor the operation of great and mightie workes, and the ſpeculation of high knowledge, when as he preferred charitie before them both, in reſpect of pietie: no more would I be thought to diſpraiſe reading of Scriptures, frequenting of Lectures, and hearing of Sermons, when as I preferred prayer before them all, in reſpect of the vnceſſant vſe we haue of it: in the dayly ſeruice of God, let euery thing be placed in his proper roome and order, becauſe they are giuen, and procéede all from him, which liketh ſo well of order, that he vouchſalfeth to be called the God of order.</p>
               <p>Surely, as touching reading of Scriptures, &amp; hearing of Sermons, we muſt néedes confeſſe both theſe to be great helps vnto the man of God, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cauſe of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Whence is faith? but of hearing, whence is hearing but
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3536:22"/>
of the word, howbeit let the vngenerate man heare the Apoſtles preach ſtrange tounges, he eſtéemes them as dronkenneſſe, let <hi>Feſtus</hi> heare <hi>S. Paul</hi> preach of Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come, he iudgeth it as madneſſe, let a multitude come to the hearing of the one of the ſelfe ſame ſermon, ſome by the hearing of the ſame are conuerted, ſome by the hearing of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame are preuerted, ſome beléeue, ſome doubt, ſome diſdaine, whats the reaſon? they vſe not al a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, the ordinary meanes of illuminating their minds, &amp; rectifiyng their wills, &amp; that is prayer: witneſſe truth it ſelfe aſke and ye ſhall receiue ſeeke and ye ſhall finde, knock and it ſhall be opened vnto you, and therefore hée which comes to heare a ſermon hauing not prepared, and ſantified his heart before hand with prayer, is like vnto a marriner which would gouerne his ſhip without a rounder, or like to a way-faring ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which wil come to his ioyrnies end, by going a diuerſe and contrary way: praier therfore vnto our preaching and your reading, is the moſt neceſſarie externall coagiuant meanes, which maketh them both effectuall, for to read the word is to receiue it more confuſedly, in great gobbots &amp; morſels, to heare the word preached, is to receiue it more orderly deuided and cut, to thinke vpon it ſeriouſly is to chew it with the cleane tooth of godly meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but to pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, to haue the true vnderſtanding of the ſame in our mindes, and a liuely féeding of it in our hearts, and conſciences, this thoroughly to degeſt it in euery part of our bodies, &amp; in euery power of our ſoules: prayer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vnto our preaching &amp; your hearing, is euen as the ſalte, which quickneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifice, it is as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leauen, which ſeaſoneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lampe, it is as the ſoule which giueth life to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, it is as the ſunne which giueth light to the world.</p>
               <p>And certainely I am perſwaded that as we preach the word ſometimes vnto men, ſo if they did pray at the ſame time together with vs, not for a faſhion ſake, with ſhowe to the eye, but in truth &amp; earneſtneſſe and from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the heart: this long planting, watring, &amp; ſowing which hath bin beſtowed, in huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dring the hearts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:3536:23"/>
men of our age, would haue yeelded more fruit of piety and godlineſſe, to the praiſe of the glory of God, bette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the whole world, and ſtopping of the mouths of our aduerſaries on both ſides, which haue ſpoken and written ſo much euill of vs. But as it was ſaid of <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> ſhort in ſtature, ſo it may be ſaid of the children of this generation, they are ſhort, they are dwarfs, they are little in ſtature, little in faith, little in worke, little in modeſty, little in ſobriety, little in temperance, little in chaſtity little in piety, little in hoſpitality, little in charity, little in vertue. To make you men of better groth, tall trées are ſtrong pillers in the houſe of God, as you come diligently to heare, ſo remember alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly to pray, to pray I ſay vnto him which hath the kéees of <hi>Dauid,</hi> openeth, and no man ſhutteth, ſhutteth and no man openeth, that he wil illuminate the beames of our vnderſtanding, that we may knowe, and direct the ſtreams and courſes of our affections, that we may do accordingly. A ſouldier goeth not to warre without his weapons, a Chriſtian, not without his prayers. <note place="margin">Caſſiodor</note>
               </p>
               <p>Be pleaſed I moſt humbly beſeech you to heare the explication of one argument more, which induceth mée in reſpect of the common neceſſity to magnifie prayer aboue hearing of ſermons. Prayer in all extremities remayneth like a Chriſtian tried companion which neuer leaueth his friend, but hearing of Lecturers, &amp; preaching of Sermons, in diuers caſes faileth. 1. A ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be ſilenced from preaching, as we know <hi>Micheas</hi> was, but he cannot be ſilenced from praying, though he be ſilenced from the vocal prayer of his tongue, yet can he not be ſilenced from the mentall prayer of his heart. 2. A man may be caſt into priſon, and fettered in cold i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was. 3. A man may be captiuate, and carried away priſoner with the Turkes and Sariſons, as we know the people of God were, with the Syrians and Babilonians. 4. A man may walke vp and downe in the wildernes, ſolitary, diſtreſſed, and afflicted, as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of the holy men of God, did before the comming of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3536:23"/>
Chriſt. 5. A man may come into a place which is ful of the botch of <hi>Aegypt</hi> &amp; dangerous infection of peſtilence.</p>
               <p>In ſome of theſe caſes, nay in euery one of theſe, how can a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniently be edified by preaching, I meane for the preſent? I deny not, but if he had bin a diligent obſeruer, he may call to mind ſondry things, which hée had heard and read, and ſo eaſe his oppreſſed &amp; diſtreſſed ſoule by them But as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayd of charity, it neuer falleth away in reſpect of continua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſo we may ſay of prayer, it neuer falleth away at any time, in any place, or vpon any occaſion <hi>Ieremie</hi> by prayer can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> 12. <hi>ſer. de tem.</hi>
                  </note> in priſon. <hi>Daniel</hi> by praier, can reioyce in the gréedy Lyons denne, the three children by prayer can triumph in the fiery flaming furnace. <hi>Iob</hi> can pray vnto God lying on his dunghill, the théefe can pray vnto God hanging on the tree, <hi>Non eſt locus vbi non eſt Deus,</hi> God is in euery place and euery place a man may po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wre out his prayers to God, yet the heddy, giddy, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſize diſciplinarian cannot perſwade himſelfe that hée can be edified by comming to the Church, vnleſſe there be a ſermon, he muſt haue a ſermon, to informe his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, he will come to the Church for that, I tell him, he hath as great néede of prayer to ſanctifie his ſoule and body, let him come to the Church for that: 1. Vnleſſe he be an infidell, a profeſſion, is to bee made here of his faith. 2. Vnleſſe he be too much a Puritant a confeſſion is to be made heere of his ſinnes. 3. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he be a ſciſmatike, his conſent is required here by ſaying, Amen, with the congregation aſſembled. 4. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he be a Traytor his prayers are to perſe forth here for the good of the king, the ſtate, and the country.</p>
               <p>Tell me doeſt thou euer read that Gods houſe was cald the houſe of preaching, this thou readeſt not, but to ſhow that the moſt vſuall and ordinary exerciſe which God will haue to be practiſed in his Church, is prayer, he thought it beſt to call the place of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip by the name of the one, and not by the name of the other, the Church was ſanctified for preaching, thou
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3536:24"/>
wilt come vnto it while this is a doing, the church is ſanctified for prayer, and hath his name of prayer, <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus mea, domus orationis.</hi> Come vnto it alſo while this is a doing. <hi>Salomon</hi> vpon, and after the dedication of the temple, went into the temple to prayer, it is read of the Publican &amp; Phariſie, that they went both to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to pray. <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>Iohn</hi> went both into the temple at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 9. hours, at the appointed time for prayer: old <hi>Anna</hi> &amp; <hi>Simeon</hi> continued dayly in the temple praying, the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple then to thoſe men, was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conuenienſt place to prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſo thought the good, ſo the bad, ſo the beléeuer, ſo the infidel, ſo the Publican, ſo the Phariſie, what a ſtrange Cockatrice egge, hath the madneſſe of certaine Sciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes hatcht amongſt vs, they wil come forſooth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, but not to prayer? O how much impiety. O how much profanenes hath the liberty &amp; licencionſnes of this our age brought forth? we read of certen of the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tient fathers, that they made their knées as hard as Camels hoofes, with continuall praying, we read of S. <hi>Ierome</hi> in moderate faſtings, &amp; wonderfull humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of himſelfe in watchings &amp; praiers: we haue S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtins</hi> meditations &amp; <hi>ſoliloquia,</hi> ſolitary ſpéeches, which he vſed vnto God, we ſee <hi>oratoria,</hi> not <hi>auditoria,</hi> orato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, churches, Colleges chappels, ſo many ſignes &amp; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of our parents manificence, &amp; vneo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parable deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion theſe men thought theſe to be the godly exerciſes of religion, to water their couch day &amp; night, for the ſins they had committed, with <hi>Dauid</hi> to chaſtice the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions of the fleſh, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaint <hi>Paul</hi> to meditate vpon their fraile ſtate &amp; miſerable conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> holy <hi>Iob</hi> to intertain poore, néedy, naked, diſtreſſed ſoules into their houſes, &amp; at their tables with faithfull <hi>Abraham:</hi> al theſe are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nay, which I ſpeake with the griefe of my ſoule, they account them vanity, &amp; ſuperſtition, &amp; men thinke that they are come to the very mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> the height of religion, if ſo be they are come to the church, turned ouer their bookes, found the text, looke on the preacher, marke his diuiſion, heard the ſermon, where is woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the conſcience, where is compunction of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> heart?
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3536:24"/>
where is mortification of the fleſh, where is deteſtation of ſin, where is ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the wrong to thy brother, where is pitty &amp; compaſſion, where are ſighes, where are teares, where are ſtrong cries &amp; gronings, where is the wiſh of the prophet <hi>Ieremy,</hi> to haue riuers of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in your heads, to wéepe day and night, for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold ſinnes ye committed againſt the maieſty of god? The end of preaching is to teach men to liue wel &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, heare S. <hi>Paul.</hi> The grace of God bringeth ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto al men, hath appeared, &amp; reacheth vs, there is the preaching what to do? mary to deny vngodlineſſe &amp; worldlines, &amp; then we ſhould liue ſoberly, iuſtly, &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily in diſpraiſe of the world: make not thy porch bigger then thy houſe it is a fooliſh kinde of building, it is the property of an Athenian to know much, and do litle, it is the duty of a chriſtian to heare often, and do ſtil that is to pray ſtil: for it is written, pray continually. This is the perfume made of the gal, &amp; liuer of the fiſh in the tooke <hi>Iob.</hi> which driueth away al kind of diuels, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminabit omne genus demoniorum,</hi> al kind of diuels, al <note place="margin">Tob. 6.</note> kind of plots, al kind of practiſes al kind of treaſons, all kind of treacherers: oh as the Angel acuiſed <hi>Toby</hi> in that place, that you would giue vs leaue (and ſo you do) which ſtand vp in theſe pulpits, as vpon the bankes, and ſpeake in your eares, which lept too too many times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond your bounds, like to the great fiſh of <hi>Tybris,</hi> vſed to deuoure, to take hold of your ſoules, to pack your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, from the fluxible watry cogitations of al world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affaires, vnto the immoueable centers of heauenly meditations, to ſette your gaules and your liuers, and your bowels, and your entralls, that is your hearts, and affections, vpon the burning coals of the incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable loue of God, and Ieſus Chriſt his Son: vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly this wil not only make a perſume which wil driue away all manner of diuels from vs, but will make for your good, to the good of Gods glory, and the good of the Church, and the good of this noble Kingdome, a moſt ſwéete, &amp; adoriferous ſauour in the noſeſtrills of God,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3536:25"/>
I will ſpeake what I intend more plainly. Your ſacred preſence (moſt dread and mightie Soueraigne) at the morning and euening Sacrifice, will induce others to preſent themſelues, they will come, they will runne, they will proſtrate themſelues, they will worſhip, they will adore in the holy Sanctuarie of God, the ſwéete o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of the oyntments of this your gratious deuotion, hath, and doth, and will drawe on others, yea many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for to follow: yea the ſtrange children will be brought to follow, vnto whom all that euer we could doe, both our preaching and praying, were the ſauour of death vnto death, euen an abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for this cauſe of ſet purpoſe haue I compiled this Sermon, according to the meaſure of grace which is giuen vnto me, haue preached the ſame in the eares of Maieſtie, the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of holineſſe, which was a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nointed with the fulneſſe of all graces, confirme &amp; continue your gratious heart, in this moſt holy and Chriſtian exerciſe of pietie and godlineſſe, that that may be ſpoken and written, ſpoken to them that are liuing, and written to the poſterities to come, of the moſt religious King <hi>Iames,</hi> that was ſpoken and written of the moſt zealous king <hi>Ioſias,</hi> that <note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 23.</note> you may match him in all things, euen by being a king as young and yonger then he, like vnto him was there not any before him, neither aroſe there any after him, which turned vnto the Lord his GOD, with all his heart, with all his minde, and with all his ſoule, to loue him, and to feare him and to ſerue him, and here imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the wiſe gouernour, reſerued the beſt Wine for the laſt, I end. Now vnto God immortall, inuiſible, and onely wiſe, the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt, thrée perſons in trinitie, one God in vnitie, be rendred all power, dominion, glory, maieſtie, and ſeruice, for euer, and for euer.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
